Guide to the Christina M. Breman Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Christina M. Breman Papers
1962-1996
RG 134
Yale University Divinity School Library
10
(26 boxes)
These papers represent the source materials gathered by Breman while preparing her dissertation, "The Association of Evangelicals in Africa: Its History, Organization, Members, Projects, External Relations, and Message", which was published in 1996. More than 8,000 photocopies from documents in the offices of the Association of Evangelicals in Africa in Nairobi, Kenya are supplemented by materials related to Dr. Tokunboh Adeyemo and Dr. Byang H. Kato. Christina Maria Breman was a missionary for the Africa Inland Mission International (AIM) who was forced by ill health to return to the Netherlands. There she completed a Ph. D. at the Theological Deparment of the University of Utrecht under missiology Dr. Jan A. B. Jongeneel.
Breman, Christina Maria, 1941-
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Christina Breman.
Biographical / Historical
Christina Maria Breman was born in 1941. She was a missionary for the Africa Inland Mission International (AIM) until forced by ill health to return to the Netherlands. There she completed a Ph. D. at the Theological Deparment of the University of Utrecht under missiology Dr. Jan A. B. Jongeneel. Her life was cut short by a recurrence of cancer.
The Association of Evangelicals in Africa, the subject of Breman's study, was established in Kenya in 1966 and now has branches in most sub Saharan countries.
Under the leadership of the first African General Secretary, Dr. Byang H. Kato from Nigeria, AEA grew as an organization and started evangelical theological training on a university level in Africa. Due to Kato's efforts, the Bangui Evangelical School of theology in the Central Africa Republic in francophone Africa was established in the 1970's. The English counterpart is the Nairobi Evangelical Graduate School of Theology.
Under Kato's successor, Dr. Tokunboh Adeyemo, also from Nigeria, the AEA became a movement with strong influence in evangelical Africa. Adeyemo also served as Chairman of the International Council of the World Evangelical Fellowship.
Scope and Contents
These papers represent the source materials gathered by Breman while preparing her dissertation, "The Association of Evangelicals in Africa: Its History, Organization, Members, Projects, External Relations, and Message", which was published in 1996. More than 8,000 photocopies from documents in the offices of the Association of Evangelicals in Africa in Nairobi, Kenya are supplemented by materials related to Dr. Tokunboh Adeyemo and Dr. Byang H. Kato.
The first nine series directly reflect the divisions created by Breman in her dissertation, while the last three are additional gathered materials. Breman's dissertation was published as The Association of Evangelicals in Africa: its history,organization, members, projects, external relations and message by Uitgeverij Boekencentrum, in1996. It has been described as a "monumental work" and "a major reference text." The primary source materials available in this collection were the basis for Breman's dissertation and provide even more extensive documentation of the Association of Evangelicals in Africa.
Arrangement
I. History of Association of Evangelicals in Africa
II. Organization of AEA
III. Members of AEA
IV. Projects of AEA
V. External Relations of AEA
VI. Message of AEA
VII. Conclusion
VIII. Appendices
IX. Literature and Sources
X. Audiotapes
XI. Adeyemo Notebooks
XII. Kato Notebooks
Evangelicalism -- Africa -- History; Adeyemo, Tokunboh; Kato, Byang H.; Association of Evangelicals in Africa
- History of Association of Evangelicals in Africa, Series I
  - Roots of AEA
    - General (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Interdenominational Foreign Missions Association (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Evangelical Fellowship of Missions Agencies (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Africa Evangelical Office (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Birth of AEA
    - Africa Evangelical Conference, Limuru, Kenya, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Articles by D. Lolatayo (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Constitution of AEA; objectives (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The term "Evangelical" and its range (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - History of AEA
    - Period of Foundation (1966-1973)
      - First General Secretary: Rev. Kenneth Lee Downing, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Acting General Secretary/ Administrative Secretary: Eric Maillefer, 1965-1966, 1968-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - President Rev. Dr. Samuel Olusigun Odunaike, 1969-1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Characteristics of the period of foundation (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Period of Expectancy (1973-1977)
      - Second General Secretary: Dr. Byang H. Kato, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13, 14)
      - Characteristics of period of expectancy (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Period of Expansion (1978- )
      - Third General Secretary: Dr. Tounboh Adeyemo, 1978-1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Characteristics of period of expansion (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - General Assemblies
    - First General Assembly, Limuru, Kenya, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Second General Assembly, Limuru, Kenya, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Third General Assembly, Bouake, Ivory Coast, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Fourth General Assembly, Lilongwe, Malawi, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Fifth General Assembly, Lusaka, Zambia, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Sixth General Assembly, Lagos, Nigeria, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
- Organization of AEA, Series II
  - General
    - Northwestern (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Southern (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 28, 29)
  - Administrative Structure
    - General Assembly (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - General Council (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Executive Council; incl. minutes (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Executive Council; incl. notes on name change (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - General Secretary (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Headquarters: Department on Administration and Finance (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Headquarters: Communications Department (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Headquarters: Discipleship and Leadership Training Dept. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Headquarters: Former Department on Ethics, Society and Development (Box 3, Folder 38-40)
    - Headquarters: Pan African Christian Women Alliance (PACWA) (Box 4, Folder 41, 42)
    - Headquarters: Sports Outreach Ministry (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Headquarters: Department on Development and Social Transformation (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - AEA Liaison and Partnership Services (Box 4, Folder 45, 46)
    - The Gospel from Africa to Europe (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Commissions
    - Theological and Christian Education Commission
      - General (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - Association of Evangelical Bible Institutes and Colleges of Africa and Madagascar (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - Theological Commission (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Christian Education Commission (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Theological and Christian Education Commission (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Evangelism and Missions Commission
      - General (Box 4, Folder 53, 54)
    - Commission on Relief and Development
      - General (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Commission on Ethics, Peace and Justice
      - General (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Communications Commission
      - General (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Stewardship and Accountability Commission
      - General (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Evangelical Focus on Children Commission
      - General (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Special Projects
    - Evangelical Peace Mission (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - Pan Africa City Pastors' Consultation (Box 5, Folder 61)
- Members of AEA, Series III
  - Full members
    - General
      - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - National Evangelical Fellowships
      - Angola: Associacao de Evangelicos de Angola (Box 5, Folder 63, 64)
      - Botswana: Evangelical Fellowship of Botswana (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - Burkina Fao: Federation des Eglises et Missions Evangeliques du Burkina Faso (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - Central African Republic: Association des Eglises Evangeliques Centrafricaines (Box 5, Folder 67, 68)
      - Chad: Entente des Eglises et Missions Evangeliques au Tchad (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - Ethiopia: Union of Evangelical Churches of Ethiopia (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - The Gambia: Evangelical Fellowship of The Gambia (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - Ghana: National Association of Evangelicals of Ghana (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - Guinea-Bissau: Igreja Evangelica de Guine-Bissau (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Ivory Coast: Federation Evangelique de la Cote d'Ivoire (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - Kenya: Evangelical Fellowship of Kenya (Box 5, Folder 75)
      - Liberia: Association of Evangelicals of Liberia (Box 5, Folder 76)
      - Malawi: Evangelical Fellowship of Malawi (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - Mozambique: Associacao Evangelica de Mocambique (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - Namibia: Namibian Evangelical Fellowship (Box 5, Folder 79)
      - Nigeria: Nigeria Evangelical Fellowship (Box 6, Folder 80)
      - Senegal: Fraternite Evangelique du Senegal (Box 6, Folder 81)
      - Sierra Leone: Evangelical Fellowship of Sierra Leone (Box 6, Folder 82)
      - South Africa: Evangelical Fellowship of South Africa (Box 6, Folder 83-85)
      - Sudan: Sudan Evangelical Christian Association (Box 6, Folder 86)
      - Swaziland: Swaziland Conference of Churches (Box 6, Folder 87)
      - Uganda: Evangelical Fellowship of Uganda (Box 6, Folder 88)
      - Zambia: Evangelical Fellowship of Zambia (Box 6, Folder 89)
      - Zimbabwe: Evangelical Fellowship of Zimbabwe (Box 6, Folder 90)
      - Central Africa: Evangelical Fellowship (Box 7, Folder 91)
      - Congo: Evangelical Alliance (Box 7, Folder 92)
      - Congo: Church of Christ (Box 7, Folder 93)
      - Evangelical Fellowship of East Africa (Box 7, Folder 94)
      - Evangelical Fellowship: Mauritius, Madagascar (Box 7, Folder 95)
      - Evangelical Literature Fellowship: East Africa (Box 7, Folder 96)
      - Non-Affiliated Fellowship (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Associate Memebers
    - General
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 98)
    - Ministry: Missions and Evangelism
      - Africa Evangelical Fellowship (Box 7, Folder 99)
      - African Inland Mission International (Box 7, Folder 100)
      - Campus Crusade for Christ International (Box 7, Folder 101)
      - Every Home for Christ: World Literature Crusade (Box 7, Folder 102)
      - Literacy and Evangelism Fellowship (Box 7, Folder 103)
      - Mission to the World (Box 7, Folder 104)
      - Navigators, Africa Region (Box 7, Folder 105)
      - OC International (Box 7, Folder 106)
      - Overseas Missionary Fellowship, South Africa (Box 7, Folder 107)
      - Scripture Mission/ Norwegian Lutheran Mission (Box 7, Folder 108)
      - SIM International (Box 7, Folder 109)
      - Evangelical Churches West Africa (Box 7, Folder 110, 111)
    - Ministry: Mass Media and Bible Associations
      - 3xM (More Message in the Media) (Box 7, Folder 112)
      - Africa Christian Press (Box 7, Folder 113)
      - Fellowship of Christian Communicators in Africa and Madagascar (Box 7, Folder 114)
      - Fellowship of Christian Communicators in Africa and Madagascar (Box 8, Folder 115)
      - International Bible Society (Box 8, Folder 116)
      - Language Recordings International (Box 8, Folder 117)
      - Trans World Radio (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Ministry: Health
      - The Leprosy Mission International (Box 8, Folder 119)
      - MAP International (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Ministry: Development, Aid, and Relief
      - Alliance Christian Development Organisation of Tanzania (Box 8, Folder 121)
      - Ambassadors Development Agency (Box 8, Folder 122)
      - Association of Christian Resource Organizations Serving Sudan (ACROSS) (Box 8, Folder 123)
      - Prison Fellowship International (Box 8, Folder 124)
      - TEAR Fund, East Africa (Box 8, Folder 125)
      - World Concern (Box 8, Folder 126)
      - World Relief Corporation (Box 8, Folder 127)
      - World Vision International (Box 8, Folder 128)
    - Ministry: Agriculture
      - Africa Co-operative Action Trust (Box 8, Folder 129)
    - Ministry: Persecuted Church
      - General (Box 8, Folder 130)
  - Special Members
    - General (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - Individual Members
    - General (Box 8, Folder 132)
- Projects of AEA, Series IV
  - Bangui Evangelical School of Theology
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9–10)
  - Nairobi Evangelical Graduate School of Theology / Nairobi International School of Theology
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10–11)
  - Accrediting Council for Theological Education in Africa
    - Miscellaneous (Box 11–12)
  - Christian Learning Materials Centre
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12–13)
  - Theological Education by Extension
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 166-167)
  - Television (TV) Ministries
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13, Folder 168)
- External Relations of AEA, Series V
  - AEA and the Evangelicals
    - World Evangelical Fellowship (Box 13, Folder 169-170)
    - Lausanne Committee for World Evangelization (Box 14, Folder 171-173)
    - Does AEA reach all Evangelicals? (Box 14, Folder 174)
  - AEA and the Pentecostal Movement and Charismatic Renewal
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 175-176)
  - AEA and the Ecumenical Movement
    - General (Box 14, Folder 177)
    - World Council of Churches (Box 14, Folder 178-179)
    - All Africa Conference of Churches (Box 14, Folder 180-183, Box 15)
    - All Africa Christian Youth Assembly (Box 15, Folder 184)
    - Evangelical Anglicans (Box 15, Folder 185)
    - Call for a Missionary Moratorium (Box 15, Folder 186)
  - AEA and the Organisation of African Instituted Churches
    - General (Box 16, Folder 187-198)
  - AEA and the Pan African Christian Leadership Assembly
    - General (Box 17, Folder 199-200)
- Message of AEA, Series VI
  - By General Secretaries and Associate General Secretary
    - Rene Daidanso ma Djongwe (Box 17, Folder 201)
  - AEA Periodicals and Other Publications
    - Periodicals
      - General (Box 17, Folder 202)
      - Africa Evangelical News (Box 17, Folder 203)
      - Perception (Box 17, Folder 204)
      - Edification (Box 17, Folder 205)
      - Evangelical MInistries (Box 17, Folder 206-207)
      - Afretics (Box 17, Folder 208)
      - Afroscope (Box 18, Folder 209-217)
      - AEAM Prayer Bulletin (Box 18, Folder 218)
      - Vision (Box 18, Folder 219-220)
      - Step Africa (Box 18, Folder 221)
    - Other Publications
      - TEXT-Africa Project (Box 19, Folder 222-223)
      - Following Jesus Series (Box 19, Folder 224)
      - Salt and Light Series (Box 19, Folder 225)
      - Partnership and Development (Box 19, Folder 226)
      - Income Generating Projects and the Church (Box 19, Folder 227)
      - AEAM History and Ministries (Box 19, Folder 228)
      - Church in Africa Today and Tomorrow (Box 19, Folder 229)
      - A Christian Mind in Changing Africa (Box 20, Folder 230)
- Final Observations and Perspectives, Series VII
  - Views of Leaders and Orientation of AEA
    - American Influence and Beyond (Box 20, Folder 231)
- Appendices, Series VIII
  - List of Participating Groups at the Foundation of AEA (Box 20, Folder 232)
  - AEA Constitution, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 233)
  - AEA Statement of Faith (Box 20, Folder 234)
  - Statement of Faith of Sister Organisations (Box 20, Folder 235)
  - Resolutions and Declarations AEA General Assemblies (Box 20, Folder 236)
  - PACWA Covenant (Box 20, Folder 237)
  - PACWA Resolutions (Box 20, Folder 238)
  - PACLA Pledge, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 239)
  - Addresses of AEA Members (Box 20, Folder 240)
  - AEA Addresses and Addresses of External Relations (Box 20, Folder 241)
  - List of ACTEA Accredited Schools and ACTEA Related Schools (Box 20, Folder 242)
  - Questionnaire to Full Members of AEA (Box 20, Folder 243)
- Literature and Sources, Series IX
  - Bibliographies
    - Bibliography Rev. Kenneth L. Downing (Box 20, Folder 244)
    - Bibliographpy Dr. Tite Tienou (Box 20, Folder 245)
  - Lists of Publications
    - List of TEE Publications by Evangel, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 246)
    - List of CLMC Publications, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 247)
    - List of ACTEA Publications, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 248)
    - List of ESD Papers, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 249)
- Audiotapes, Series X
  - Dr. Kato - AIM Conference, 1975 (Box 21)
  - AEAM 6th General Assembly - Opening, 1993 Oct 31 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Interview, Crispin Cole, 1993 Nov 1 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Turaki, Kenoti, 1993 Nov 2 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Official opening, 1993 Nov 4 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Adeyemo, Cole, workshops, 1993 Nov 5 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Persecuted church, PACWA, Adeyemo, 1993 Nov 5 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Adeyemo, Brother Andrew, 1993 Nov 6 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Anne v. d. Biji, Adeyemo, 1993 Nov 6, 8 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Bible study, business meeting, 1993 Nov 8 (Box 21)
  - General Assembly - Business meeting, 1993 Nov 8 (Box 21)
- Adeyemo Notebooks, Series XI
  - Notebook 1
    - Bibliographies (Box 22, Folder 250)
    - Diverse typescripts (Box 22, Folder 251)
    - Lectures, papers, 1976-1992 (Box 22, Folder 252)
    - From File A, AEA headquarters (Box 22, Folder 253)
    - From File B, AEA headquarters (Box 22, Folder 254)
    - From File C, AEA headquarters (Box 22, Folder 255)
    - From File D, AEA headquarters (Box 22, Folder 256)
    - From File E, AEA headquarters (Box 22, Folder 257)
    - Selected typescripts, 1989-1991 (Box 22, Folder 258)
    - Unpublished theses and papers, 1976 (Box 22, Folder 259)
  - Notebook II
    - Unpublished theses and papers, ch. 1 and 2, 1976, 1986 (Box 22, Folder 260)
    - Unpublished theses and papers, ch. 3 (Box 22, Folder 261)
    - Unpublished theses and papers, ch. 4 and 5 (Box 23, Folder 262)
    - Unpublished theses and papers (conclusion) (Box 23, Folder 263)
    - Books, booklets, brochures, edited workds, 1981-1994 (Box 23, Folder 264)
    - Articles, 1973-1983 (Box 23, Folder 265-267)
  - Notebook III
    - Selected literature on Adeyemo, 1983, 1994 (Box 23, Folder 268)
    - Reviews on Adeyemo's publications, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 269)
    - Reviews by Adeyemo (Box 23, Folder 270)
    - Articles, 1984-1996 (Box 23, Folder 271-273)
- Kato Notebooks, Series XII
  - Notebook I
    - Bibliography, 1975 (Box 24, Folder 274)
    - Articles, 1962-1994 (Box 24, Folder 275-277)
    - Books, booklets, brochures, 1976, 1981 (Box 24, Folder 278)
    - Typescripts, 1973-1975 (Box 24, Folder 279-281)
  - Notebook II
    - Other info. on/by Kato, 1971-1982 (Box 25, Folder 290)
    - Selected literature on B. Kato, 1976-1993 (Box 25, Folder 291-292)
    - Reviews on Kato's publications, 1977-1980 (Box 26, Folder 293)
    - Posthumous articles, 1975-1989 (Box 26, Folder 294-296)